<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Doctor Chamberlain visited with a bunch of his own grapes, gathered out of his own packet of letters: to know whether my answer to his question gave satisfaction, and that by his reply to partake of those rare gifts of the spirit, which he proffered to publish in Black-fryers Church. Also an answer to Dr Chamberlains reply, concerning sprinkling the baptized. / By Thomas Bakewel.</title>
            <author>Bakewell, Thomas, b. 1618 or 19.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1650</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 65 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 16 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A77749</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B532</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E601_4</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R206402</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99865563</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99865563</idno>
            <idno type="VID">117808</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A77749)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 117808)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 92:E601[4])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Doctor Chamberlain visited with a bunch of his own grapes, gathered out of his own packet of letters: to know whether my answer to his question gave satisfaction, and that by his reply to partake of those rare gifts of the spirit, which he proffered to publish in Black-fryers Church. Also an answer to Dr Chamberlains reply, concerning sprinkling the baptized. / By Thomas Bakewel.</title>
                  <author>Bakewell, Thomas, b. 1618 or 19.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>28 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for John Dallam, and are to be sold at his shop in Black-fryers neer Carter-lane,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1650.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A reply to: Chamberlen, Peter. To my beloved friends and neighbours of the Black-Fryers.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "May 15.".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Chamberlen, Peter, 1601-1683. --  To my beloved friends and neighbours of the Black-Fryers.</term>
               <term>Baptism --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:117808:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Doctor <hi>Chamberlain</hi> VISITED WITH A Bunch of his own Grapes, Gathered out of His own Packet of Letters: To know whether my Anſwer to his Queſtion gave ſatisfaction, and that by his Reply to partake of thoſe rare Gifts of the Spirit, which he proffered to publiſh in <hi>Black-fryers</hi> Church.</p>
            <p>Alſo an Anſwer to D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Chamberlains</hi> Reply, concerning Sprinkling the Baptized.</p>
            <p>By THOMAS BAKEWEL.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>DEUT. 32.32.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Their vine is of the vine of Sodom: and their grapes are grapes of gall, their cluſters are bitter.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>John Dallam,</hi> and are to be ſold at his ſhop in <hi>Black-fryers</hi> neer <hi>Carter</hi>-lane, 1650.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:117808:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:117808:2"/>
            <head>A Viſit to Doctor <hi>Chamberlain,</hi> to make Reply, if he be not ſatisfied, that the cenſure of his Dream fall not on himſelf, to be left hardened in blind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>SInce I wrote my Anſwer to your Queſtion, concerning</hi> Sprinkling the Baptized, <hi>you have publiſhed all your Letters, which you ſent to Doctor</hi> Gouge <hi>about it; and alſo a ſcurrilous Libel, full of railing language, you have Printed with them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>This railing Rabſhakeh ſaith, That this reverend Miniſter of Jeſus Chriſt</hi> knows not of what ſpirit he is, and that he hath not the Spirit of Chriſt, nor of a private Chriſtian; he is none of Chriſts Miniſter, but a Worldling; he is dumb, and dare not ſpeak; he is not fit to have the charge of Souls: he is devil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſh minded, and ought to be caſt out, or healed: Chriſt will not have ſuch ſpirits to be Miniſters of his Kingdome: He is more for the world, and his own eaſe, then for Chriſt, and your good: He chuſeth to keep his people in darkneſs, leſt a ſtronger then he ſhould come in, and diſpoſſeſſe him, by bringing in the glorious Light of the Goſpel. <hi>Thus terming our Miniſters to evil ſpirits, and himſelf and his Faction to Jeſus Chriſt, who on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly is able to cast them out, and to take poſſeſſion of the Soul, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Redeemer of it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>But what is the offence given by Doctor</hi> Gouge, <hi>for this man thus to rail on him?</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:117808:3"/>
            <p>Anſw. <hi>Nothing but this,</hi> Chriſt, <hi>ſaith he,</hi> anſwered all queſtion, and ſo ſhould he. <hi>But Sir, why did not you come to him for an Anſwer? How can you endure to hear this man to rail thus, before you have tryed the Doctors faithfulneſſe? when he ſo lovingly invited you to come unto him, and if you pleaſed, to bring a Friend with you: But your motion was rather for his Pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pit, then for his Anſwer, more for diviſion then for ſatisfaction: rather preſuming to teach the Doctor, then to be taught by him. Now Chriſt would not anſwer thoſe that came to</hi> cavil at his Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, <hi>Joh.</hi> 18.19, 20. <hi>nor thoſe that queſtioned his</hi> Authority, <hi>Mat.</hi> 21.27. <hi>nor his</hi> accuſers before <hi>Pilate, Mat.</hi> 27, 12, 14. Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo <hi>his Miniſters are forbidden to</hi> caſt pearls before ſwine, <hi>or</hi> to give holy things to dogs, <hi>Mat.</hi> 7.6. <hi>or</hi> to reprove ſcorners, <hi>Prov.</hi> 8.7, 8.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>But this railer goes on, not onely againſt him, but againſt all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Miniſters that are faithful to Jeſus Chriſt, ſaying,</hi> They are all his fellow ſpirits, they are all agreed, and they muſt all be caſt out, and enter in no more, but into a ſwiniſh generation, who dig their way to Hell, with whom they ſhall run violently head<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long to the deep: Therefore, <hi>ſaith he,</hi> they are deaf to hear the Word of God, and dumb to ſpeak the truth thereof, though up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it they will ſpeak till they foam againe: But, <hi>ſaith he,</hi> ſee that they do not deceive you, for they are evil ſpirits, ſeeking to devour you: <hi>And ſo he concludes, ſaying,</hi> Receive this, as from Chriſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Now whom this Railer is, I know not, yet ſome think him to be one</hi> Evins, <hi>that was in Newgate for profeſſing himſelf to be Jeſus Chriſt; and not unlikely, for ſaith he,</hi> Receive this as from Chriſt: <hi>And alſo, that ſtronger man, who alone is able to call out evil ſpirits, he applies to himſelf, or ſome of his Faction: But then he ſeems to recant of all the evil that he hath ſpoken against the Doctor, ſaying,</hi> Not that I hate him, for I have many Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons to love him in truth. <hi>But I ſay, if all were true here ſpoken by this Railer, what Reaſons can he have to love him in truth? or if falſe, what a horrible wretch is he thus to reproach him? But God hath made his own Conſcience to check his railing tongue, confeſſing to have Reaſons to love him in truth, and yet they muſt not be made known.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:117808:3"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Now I ſhall ſhew that you are led by the ſame ſpirit, for theſe Reaſons: Firſt, You ſay, That</hi> this Raler is a Meſſenger come from Chriſt, <hi>and that</hi> no man can deny it: <hi>which ſhews, that the ſame ſpirit rules in both. Secondly, This Railer ſaith to you,</hi> Set theſe things in order, and ſend them to Black fryers: <hi>and this alſo you have done, although with ſome difficulty, becauſe as you ſay of the illiterateneſſe of his compoſure, which he left for you to perfect; which ſhews, that you are led by the ſame ſpirit. Third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, This Railer ſaith to you,</hi> Write, and print, and ſend them; <hi>and this alſo you have done. Fourthly, This Railer ſaith to you,</hi> See that you uſe not my name; <hi>and accordingly you have conceal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed it, although it is very likely you know it. Fifthly, He rails upon this reverend Miniſter, notwithſtanding be hath many Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons to love him in truth: ſo you argue the Doctors friendſhip, his age his learning, his exemplary retiredneſs and ſtrictneſs of living; yea, and expreſly you ſay that you love him; and yet one Dream, ſug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſted by the Devil, will make you to leave him, as you ſay</hi> hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in blindneſſe, <hi>which comprehends all that the Railer hath ſpoken. Sixthly, You have given ſuch way to this foul spirit, as to defuſe what he hath ſuggeſted; for the Doctor anſwered to your question, concerning</hi> Sprinkling the Baptized, <hi>that you might come to him, and alſo bring a Friend with you, if you pleaſed: But to the other queſtion, whether it ſhould be disputed in his Church, he would be better adviſed, and well he might; for what Shepherd would ſuffer the Wolf to dispute among the Sheep? But you, like a falſe witneſſe, apply his Anſwer to the wrong queſtion, and from that falſe ground take an occaſion to inſult over him, and dare him to take advice with ſeveral Divines, and alſo with the whole Synod, and make it as pulique as he would: Thus you have publiſhed your pride and vanity with leſſe diſcretion then your ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved Friend, this railing Libeller, who is ſenſible that his name is contemptible among the people.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sir, Having no Reply to my Anſwer, I ſhall make bold to ſpeak unto you in your own words, and language, expreſſed in your Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, thus, Was your queſtion to Doctor</hi> Gouge <hi>a matter of Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, or was it not? If not, why did you ſo often reiterate your Letters, with ſuch vehemency for an Anſwer? and that he would deal clearly in this buſineſſe, as he valued the Souls of men? On
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:117808:4"/>the other ſide, If it was a matter of Salvation, why did you not come to him, when he ſo lovingly envited you to come, and if you pleaſed, to bring a Friend with you alſo? Again, either you were ignorant of that point, or not: If not, why did you propound that queſtion! Is it not your own inference to ſay,</hi> He that asketh ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, is ignorant of the thing he asketh advice in? <hi>So that if you were not blinde, you would not ask whether it be day. Do not you alſo ſay, That</hi> all doubts are for want of Faith or Knowledg? <hi>Or did you onely propound this to try the Doctor, whether he was willing to give you an Anſwer? and the mean time you remain unwilling to come unto him for it? Will not this be a greater ſhame to you, then if you had never propounded that queſtion to him who formerly was your Shepherd?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sir, The Railing Libeller, whom you ſay comes in the name of Chriſt, ſaith,</hi> That this is a profound queſtion, and moſt neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary to be cleared, and put forth, by one who ſeeth the Ax layd to the root of Religion, and the Watchmen aſleep, at this time of diſtreſſe and diſtraction amongſt the flock of Chriſt; ſome de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nying this Fundamental Ordinance, to be of any effect, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers deny it to Infants as lawful, and others deny ſprinkling to be of God: Now a full Anſwer, <hi>ſaith he,</hi> to this queſtion will clear all, and heal all doubts and diſtractions: <hi>Therefore remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber your Charge; he hath ſhewed that you have ſet your hand to the Plough, and if you look back, he ſaith,</hi> You are unfit for the Kingdom of God.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sir, I long to ſee thoſe excellent vertues and operations of the Spirit, which you boaſt to have received, ſince you turn'd</hi> Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptiſt: <hi>Let not thoſe tranſcendent gifts be put under a Buſhel, but ſet thoſe New-Lights on a Candleſtick, to give Light to all that are in the Houſe. Sir, You promiſed and proffered to ſhew thoſe gifts to Doctor</hi> Gouge, <hi>to teach him knowledg; let me re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt the ſame favor alſo, I hope you will be no respecter of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons in the things of God: I have waited long for your Anſwer, therefore rather teach Babes then Doctors, rather Sheep then Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herds. Now if you ſhould claim the Popes title, to be</hi> a Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herd of Shepherds, <hi>to teach the Shepherd, and not the Sheep, I ſhould much doubt that thoſe admirable gifts are but the depths of Satan, as they ſpeak,</hi> Rev. 2 24. <hi>whereby he frequently deludes</hi> Anabaptiſts.</p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:117808:4"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Sir, You ſay, that you wrote to the late King, and I ſee that you have written to a Doctor of Divinity: But I hope you do not think it to be a diſparagement to write to them of meaner quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty: Is your matter ſo excellent that no other men may partake of it? Suppoſe you were a King, or a Doctor not cast out of the Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, I hope ſometimes other men may hear ſome of your admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble matters, which onely becomes Kings and Doctors to hear.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sir, I hope your tranſcendent gifts are not of that quality to periſh in the uſing: If they be divine gifts, they will increaſe by uſing. Now if yours be ſuch, what hurt is it to impart with them for advantage? If you keep your Talent in a napkin, you will of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend the Lord, who gave it to be improved for the good of your ſelf &amp; others; but it ſeems you know this already, and have told your loving Neighbors of</hi> Black-fryers, <hi>how that you, being converted, ought in duty to ſtrengthen your Brethren. Now I hope you will not make ſuch conſtruction of the word</hi> Brethren, <hi>as to ſhut me out of that Brotherhood. Sir, the</hi> Meſſenger of Chriſt, <hi>as you call that railing Libeller, I hope, hath made a better conſtruction of your Dream, then to leave me alſo with Doctor</hi> Gouge <hi>hardened in blindneſſe; therefore let me hear from you, whether my Anſwer gave ſatisfaction, or not; and if it did, give God the praiſe: and if it did not, I deſire to know wherein it was wanting, becauſe I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to have more charity of you, then to leave you hardened in blindneſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>BY</hi> Thomas Bakewel.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:117808:5"/>
            <head>An ANSWER to Doctor <hi>Chamberlains</hi> Reply, concerning Sprinkling of the Baptized.</head>
            <p>UPon the 24. of <hi>March</hi> I ſent my firſt P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>per to Doctor <hi>Chamberlain,</hi> that now is publiſhed, and he that received it, promiſed an Anſwer in two days; and now upon the ſeventh of <hi>April</hi> his Reply came to me ſo ſtufft with Sophiſtry and fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity, that it is enough to terrifie a gracious heart even in he Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petition of it.</p>
            <p>His firſt page is a bundle of falſities: He ſaith, <hi>That he ſent four times to my houſe, to return me an Anſwer, and that I either was not, or would not be at home:</hi> Theſe are all falſe, he ſent but twice; The firſt time I was at Church, the ſecond time the Meſſenger ſpake with me, not to return me an Anſwer, but to ask me theſe queſtions, <hi>Why did you not come to hear your Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter read? and why did you not come to juſtifie it? and did you write it your ſelf, or did ſome other help you?</hi> Then he ſaith, <hi>That I call the ſeventh of April, being the Lords day, Palmſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day,</hi> which he never heard me; and <hi>the Sabbath,</hi> which it ſeems he will not: and that <hi>I tell my friends that I have defied Iſrael;</hi> and that I ſhould ſay, <hi>none durſt anſwer me;</hi> which are both falſe: And that I ſhould ſay, <hi>He promiſed to anſwer;</hi> which alſo is falſe, although there was a promiſe made by another that it ſhould be done. Then he ſaith, <hi>He had no copy of what I printed,</hi> when as there was a whole quire ſent him, beſides the manuſcript that I ſent him; yet he ſaith, <hi>He had not known of it, had not another given him one.</hi> But to what purpoſe are all thoſe falſities, if he were not given over to the Father of lyes? They concern not the point in Controverſie. But Mr Doctor, are theſe the gifts of the Spirit you boaſt ſo much of, to have ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed publiquely in Doctor <hi>Gouges</hi> Church? It is true, they are the gifts of thoſe lying ſpirits in the mouths of <hi>Ahabs</hi> Prophets, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 18 21. But Sir, Be ware of the lyers portion, <hi>Revel.</hi> 21.8.</p>
            <p>Then you ſay, <hi>That I am the Cats paw, dabling in Greek:</hi> I
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:117808:5"/>ſuppoſe you ſpeak comparatively, which having no reſemblance, ſhews your weakneſs of learning; for a Cat to dabble in Greek cannot, and in water will not, or at leaſt as ſeldom as you dabble in the truth: but I muſt leave dabling.</p>
            <p>Then you trouble your ſelf that Mr <hi>Downame</hi> ſhould give me his <hi>Imprimatur,</hi> and that our Miniſters ſhould ſuffer a Layman to take upon him their Function: How now Mr Doctor! what do you reprove another, and do the ſame things? <hi>Thou that ſayſt, another ſhould not ſteal, doſt thou ſteal? Thou that judgeſt another, condemneſt thy ſelf for doing the ſame things:</hi> See <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.1, 21. But yet Mr Doctor I do not take upon me the Miniſters Function: Was I ever the mouth of God to the Congregation, by preaching unto them? or their mouth unto God by prayer? or did I ever adminiſter the Sacraments to the people? If not, theſe are falſly ſpoken of me, although your ſelfe, and other Lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men amongſt <hi>Anabaptists,</hi> frequently do them: But cavilling <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> have alwayes ſomething to ſay againſt thoſe that are truly orthodox. If our learned Miniſters write any Tract, then they ſay they have nothing but <hi>Humane Learning,</hi> they have not the <hi>Spirit;</hi> and if any illiterate man ſhall write againſt them, then he wants Learning: but if for them, then ſay you in your firſt Letter, <hi>God gives poor Fiſhermen the Spirit, which he doth not to learned Clarks.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Then you would make the world beleeve that you are of a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry humble ſpirit, and you deſerve not the title of <hi>Tyrus:</hi> But Pride breakes out, and ſpoiles all, ſaying that which you falſely charged me withall, That our Miniſters durſt not anſwer you, there was none ſo bold; yet ſtill you would have me bear the name, and keep the vice your ſelfe, ſaying, <hi>I</hi> preſume to anſwer for Doctor <hi>Gouge,</hi> ſuppoſing my ſelfe the abler man, which will not follow, although it may be more willing, becauſe it is like he knows the temper of your ſpirit better then <hi>I.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Then you ſay that I except againſt you for asking Dr <hi>Gouge</hi> a queſtion, becauſe he is ancient, when as multitude of years ſhould <hi>teach wiſdom, Iob</hi> 32.7. and of whom ſhould we enquire, but of them that take upon them the Office? ſhould not the <hi>Prieſts lips keep Knowledg? Mal.</hi> 2.7. But here, like <hi>Corah,</hi> you ſay, he takes the Office upon him; but beware of <hi>Corahs</hi> Judgment:
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:117808:6"/>See <hi>Numb.</hi> 16.3.35.40. You charge him, but condemne your ſelfe, doing the ſame thing: But why did not you come to learn at his mouth? which is your duty from that Text, <hi>Mal.</hi> 2.7. Neither do I except againſt asking the Doctor a queſtion, becauſe he is ancient, but becauſe you more required his Pulpit then his Anſwer; to make diviſion rather then to ſeeke for ſatisfaction: Neither is it fit, I ſay, that ancient Miniſters ſhould be dayly troubled with all the vain queries that <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> may put un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them.</p>
            <p>But then you are troubled that I ſhould not give you leave to ſtate your own queſtion, which was ſo ſtated, that the anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of it, as it was, would ſtart up more queſtions, which would be endleſſe: Therefore it was my deſire to confine the queſtion onely to <hi>Sprinkling the Baptized,</hi> and leave Infants for another queſtion: at this you cavil, asking, <hi>Whether they muſt firſt be baptized, and then ſprinkled,</hi> which ſhews of what ſpirit you are: as if I ſhould ſay, Such a man hath married a wife, for which you ſhould accuſe me, for ſaying, he marryed her that was a wife at that time to another man. Then you ſay, That Doctor <hi>Gouge</hi> doth acknowledge, <hi>That Sprinkling and Bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing Infants is but a Tradition of the Church:</hi> I queſtion the truth of it: But I ſay they are ſuch Traditions of the Church as that they are not mans Inventions, nor by man to be aboliſhed.</p>
            <p>Then you come to my firſt Argument in theſe words, <hi>The Lord foretold, that in the times of the Goſpel his People ſhould be ſprinkled with clean water, Ezek.</hi> 36.25. To this you propound many queries, thus; <hi>Whether Sprinkling here be meant Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme; or, by cleane water, the elementary water; and</hi> you <hi>bee meant Infants, and the time then be meant the time of the Goſpel with the Gentiles, or the time of the glorious Calling of the Jews: or whether Sprinkling doe not allude to that Sprinkling under the Law, they not knowing</hi> Johns nor Chriſts <hi>Baptiſm, and whether</hi> pure water <hi>be not meant the Holy Ghoſt in the language of Chriſt?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To this I anſwer; Let them be <hi>Iewes</hi> or <hi>Gentiles,</hi> in reſpect of Country, bond or free, male or female, Infants or of full age; all in the Chriſtian Church have right to Baptiſme: Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther can this Text look back to the Jewiſh Sprinklings under
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:117808:6"/>the Law, becauſe it is a Prophecy or Promiſe to come hereafter: neither can this be meant of the Eſſence of the Holy Ghoſt, to be ſprinkled, which is uncommunicable; and for the graces or operations of the Holy Ghoſt, promiſed to be beſtowed in the latter dayes, they are no where promiſed to be by ſprinkling a few drops: <hi>But, ſaith the Lord, it ſhall come to paſſe, that I will poure out my Spirit, Ioel</hi> 2.28. <hi>I will poure water upon him that is thirsty, and floods upon the dry ground, I will poure my Spirit upon thy ſeed, and my bleſſing upon thy off-ſpring, Iſa.</hi> 44.3. Now ſee the Apoſtles Expoſition of theſe Texts; <hi>It ſhall come to paſs ſaith God, that I will pour out my ſpirit, Act.</hi> 2.17. And, ſaith Chriſt himſelf, <hi>Out of his belly ſhall flow rivers of living water;</hi> but this ſpake he of the Spirit, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 7.38, 39. Neither is it likely that the Promiſe of Grace, in the fulneſſe of Chriſts Kingdome, ſhould be no more but a few drops ſprinkled, which they had when theſe Promiſes were made; ſo that it remaines, that this Sprinkling here fore-told to be with clean water, is the Elemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary water ſprinkled upon the Baptized as the outward form, which may ſignifie all that abundance of grace promiſed to be then beſtowed upon the Chriſtian Church. And Mr Doctor, theſe things I am confident ſhall be accompliſhed, although you taxe me with Lay-ignorance, and to be talketive; and you be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve that theſe miſtakes will make them to keep the ſtaff in their own hands, and not to ſuffer ſuch, though never ſo zealous and devout, to betray their cauſe: To this, I know not whom you mean, but God forbid, that for any private cauſe, any Power on Earth ſhould ſuppreſſe the Truth, although they have the ſtaff of power in their hand. But then you conclude, <hi>All that can be ſaid upon this place is onely a Promiſe what God will do, and not a Command what man muſt do.</hi> Anſ. It may be the outward form of Baptiſm by <hi>ſprinkling of water,</hi> for all that; for <hi>God</hi> may do it by Inſtruments: The <hi>Phariſees</hi> heard that Jeſus made and baptized more Diſciples then <hi>Iohn,</hi> though Jeſus himſelf baptized not, but his Diſciples, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 4.1, 2. <hi>And they came to Iohn, ſaying, He that was with thee beyond Iordan, baptizeth, Ioh.</hi> 3.26. but not him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf. But admit it was Chriſt himſelf that baptizeth, yet it is with the Holy <hi>Ghoſt,</hi> when <hi>Iohn</hi> baptizeth with water, <hi>Mat.</hi> 3.11. Thus Chriſt makes the outward Forme by Sprinkling ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectual,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:117808:7"/>by ſanctifying and cleanſing his Church <hi>with the waſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of water by the Word, Eph.</hi> 5.26. And thus Chriſt, when he waſhed his Diſciples feet, waſhed and cleanſed their Souls from ſin, or elſe they had had no part with him, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 13.8. and yet not without that outward Form.</p>
            <p>But then you are troubled that I ſhould ſay, <hi>That water in the Sacrament ſignifies the Blood of Chriſt,</hi> ſaying, <hi>Where doth the Scripture ſay ſo?</hi> But <hi>I</hi> ſay if you take away the thing ſignified from the Element, you deſtroy the Sacrament much like the <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pist,</hi> who will have the Element of Bread turned into the very Body of Chriſt: But in ſo doing you ſpoile the Ordinance, as well by plunging as ſprinkling; and yet at the end of this Secti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, you confeſſe, <hi>That ſprinkling the Conſcience with the blood of Chriſt, and waſhing the body with water,</hi> from the ſame Text that I quote, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.22. <hi>comprehends the two compleat parts of baptiſm;</hi> and yet you would drown the ſence by the <hi>Iewiſh waſhings,</hi> ſaying, <hi>They had ſprinkling with water, Lev.</hi> 14.7. <hi>Num.</hi> 8.7. <hi>diſtinct from ſprinkling with blood, Exod.</hi> 12.22.29.21. <hi>and both diſtinct from baths and waſhings, Levit.</hi> 15.5. <hi>to</hi> 27. in divers other places: <hi>And we have under the Goſpel Baptiſm diſtinct from the Lords Supper, and the Holy Ghoſt is punctual, Ioh.</hi> 19.34. But that text onely proves, that Chriſt is our Sanctification and Juſtification, ſignified by that water and blood: ſee other Texts parallel, 1 <hi>Ioh.</hi> 5.6. <hi>This is he that came by water and blood to be Righteouſneſſe, Sanctification, and Redemption,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.30. but not punctual to diſtinguiſh the two Sacraments, for one of them to Juſtifie, and the other to Sanctifie; and leaſt of all punctual to diſtinguiſh the outward Formes of the two Sacraments; for ſuppoſe you ſay, here is water, the outward Forme of Baptiſme, yet Mr Doctor, here is no bread and wine, the Forme of the other Sacrament: Then you ſay, <hi>If the Iewes had confounded the ſprinkling of water with that of blood, they would have been negligent: in thoſe things they were to be exact; and if we ſhould do ſo, we ſhould ſoon arrive at ſpiritual Babel, which is rife with many who think themſelves ſpiritual.</hi> But Mr Doctor, our difference is betweene ſprinkling and plunging, and we ſhall diſtinguiſh the two Sacraments, as well as you: And you confeſſe, that the Jewes did keep them diſtinct, that of water and that of blood, although both were adminiſtred by ſprinkling: How much eaſier is it for us to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſh
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:117808:7"/>between drinking wine, and ſprinkling with water, at our two Sacraments? and yet although the outward parts of the Sacraments differ, yet thethings ſignified do not ſo differ; for ſaith Mr <hi>Perkins</hi> on <hi>Galat</hi> pag. 214. line 32. <hi>Water reſembleth Chriſt crucified with all his merits: The blood of Chriſt cleanſeth from all ſin,</hi> 1 <hi>Ioh.</hi> 1.7. And alſo faith he, <hi>The water reſembleth the inward waſhing by the Spirit, and both by Iuſtification and Sanctification,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.11. <hi>Tit.</hi> 3.5. <hi>and other ſignes, as death, and burial of ſin, and reſurrection to newneſſe of life:</hi> And this is all that can be gathered both from the Jewiſh and Chriſtian Sacramental waſhings and cleanſings, under the Law, and under the Goſpel, which doth not at all take away ſprinkling the bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized, but rather confirmes it to be of God, and not of man.</p>
            <p>Alſo, you have confeſſed, <hi>That the outward Forme and the thing ſignified ſhould go together,</hi> from many Texts, <hi>Matt.</hi> 3.11. <hi>Mark</hi> 1. <hi>Luke</hi> 3. <hi>Act.</hi> 1.5. <hi>&amp;</hi> 2.58. <hi>&amp;</hi> 10. <hi>Yea, God will not do the one without the other; the outward waſhing, and the inward ſanctification, ought to goe together; not the outward waſhing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone, but the inward anſwer of a good Conſcience towards God, through Ieſus Christ,</hi> 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.21. And yet I ſmell a deſigne you have in thoſe expreſſions drawn from that Text, <hi>Mat.</hi> 3.7. <hi>The Phariſees and Sadduces without fruits of Repentance were not ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to the Baptiſme of water:</hi> Hence it may be you will ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, That fruites muſt appeare on all, before they ſhall have the outward Forme of Baptiſme, that you may exclude <hi>Infants:</hi> it is true, theſe Sectaries <hi>Iohn</hi> refuſed, as unworthy of admittance till Reformation; but all other that were willing, were admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: And beſides, the caſe of <hi>Infants,</hi> whoſe Parents are admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, is not the ſame with thoſe that are converted from Judaiſme, or Heatheniſme, to the Chriſtian Faith; the Parents and their ſeed are ſet apart for holy uſes, as members of the viſible Church; although they want real infuſed Holineſs, they have a right to the Ordinances: yea, if but one of the Parents be admitted, the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren are holy, faith <hi>Paul,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.14. But this point hath beene ſo ſufficiently cleared by others, that <hi>I</hi> ſhall wave it.</p>
            <p>You come to my ſecond Argument: <hi>The ſigne muſt be viſible, to put us in minde of the thing ſignified: The token of the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:117808:8"/>ſhall be ſeene, Gen.</hi> 9.11, 14. <hi>The People being ſprinkled, muſt behold the blood of the Covenant, Exod.</hi> 24.8. <hi>The ſenſes muſt bee exerciſed, Hebr.</hi> 5.14. <hi>but hee that is plunged under water, can neither hear the words of inſtitution, nor ſee the ſigne, therefore un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit to uſe that Ordinance.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To this you ſay, <hi>Sprinkling is but lately allowed of by the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectory, but not by the booke of Common Prayer:</hi> But what of that? Doth antiquity of error make it ever the better?</p>
            <p>But you ask, whether by our Rule wee doe not make a face Chriſtian, yea a ſpeckled faced Chriſtian, by ſprinkling here and there a drop? as if the water in Baptiſm were of a ſtaining, and not of a cleanſing nature: moreover, ſaith he, if we allow Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm, to ſignifie the waſhing away of ſin, as all Catechiſms im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply, would you waſh the face and outward appearance of ſinne, and ſo make an outſide <hi>Phariſee-Chriſtian?</hi> But <hi>I</hi> ſay, would you have the Elementary water go any further then the outſide, you that plunge all over, yet all is but the outſide; and the more of outſide in any duty, the more you are Phariſee-like: and that the outward Forme of Baptiſme by water ſignifies the cleanſing from ſinne, <hi>I</hi> grant; but yet one drop applyed to the body in that Ordinance, may ſignifie the greateſt cleanſing from ſinne: and if you ſtand ſo much upon your meaſure of water in this Ordinance, let mee in your next knowe your quantity, and by what meaſure you try the fulneſſe of that quantity, or elſe <hi>I</hi> ſhall ſuſpect that you hold him moſt worthy to come to the Lords Table that will drinke moſt wine, as well as to hold, hee is beſt baptized that is plunged in moſt water: The mean time <hi>I</hi> ſhall hold, a drop on the face may ſignifie more grace in the Soul then ever any <hi>Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptiſts</hi> attained unto. Again, Circumciſion on one part ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied mortification of ſinn in all parts: or elſe, by your Argument, when they circumciſed one part, they ſhould have flayed the skin off all over, and where it was not ſo flayed, the ſinne was not mortified. Theſe are your excellent gifts, it ſeemes, you would have publiſhed in Doctor <hi>Gouges</hi> Pulpit.</p>
            <p>But you get you back to the Common-Prayer Booke, made by the <hi>Pope</hi> and <hi>Prelates,</hi> and to them it ſeemes you will ſticke: And then you ſay, <hi>It was the practice of Chriſt and His Apoſtles, and thoſe that we call Fathers:</hi> But Mr Doctor, wee muſt have
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:117808:8"/>ſome Proofes; Old Birds will not be catched with Chaff. But then you ask, <hi>Would we have our faces buried with Chriſt in Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme, and baptized into his Death, and have our face onely riſe with him? or would you have onely an outſide death to ſin, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection to life in Chriſt? Col.</hi> 2.12. <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.3, 4. <hi>Or would you make Chriſt onely a vizzard for your face?</hi> But Mr Doctor, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though the Death of Chriſt and his Burial be called <hi>Baptiſmes, Luk.</hi> 12.50. and waſhing the body when dead be called <hi>Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.29. <hi>This cup,</hi> ſaith Chriſt, <hi>ye ſhall drink of: we ſhall be baptized with thoſe Baptiſmes, Mat.</hi> 20.23. But I hope Mr Doctor you will not kill your Diſciples, and waſh their bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, and bury them, this is ſomething harſh; it is well it is but one Doctors Opinion: I thought I had cleared this upon <hi>Page</hi> 7, &amp; 8. of the <hi>Dippers Plunged.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But you ask, <hi>If Infants can behold the ſign, and make that uſe of it; will they not rather ſhut their eyes?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> Firſt, All are not Infants, ſome may be converted from the <hi>Turkes</hi> and <hi>Iewes</hi> to the Chriſtian Faith that are of full age, and theſe having their ſenſes, they ought to uſe them: although Infants, through the defect of nature, cannot make uſe of the ſign, nor of the words of Inſtitution; yet it is damnable for them of full age to ſtop their eares like the deafe Adder at the Word of God: ſee <hi>Prov.</hi> 28.9. <hi>Pſa.</hi> 58.4. <hi>Mat.</hi> 13.15. <hi>Revel.</hi> 2.7.</p>
            <p>Again, the words of inſtitution are to be ſpoken in the act of baptizing; <hi>Baptizing them in the Name of the Father, Son, and Holy Ghoſt, Mat</hi> 28.19. Now for a man or woman to be under water all that while, it may drown them, and he that ſhall place theſe words either before or after, it is his own invention, and none of Chriſts inſtitution: But you harpe upon this ſtring, to exclude <hi>Infants,</hi> ſaying, <hi>Thoſe that are baptized according to the Scriptures, doe both heare and know them, before they are plunged, although pronouncing the words do not the worke, but the obedience of beeing baptized in the Name of the Lord. It</hi> ſeemes by theſe words, that you hold <hi>a baptizing in the Name of the Lord</hi> before the outward Forme of baptizing by water, flat againſt the <hi>Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture:</hi> ſee <hi>Act.</hi> 10.48. <hi>&amp;</hi> 19.3, 5. And <hi>Iohn</hi> ſaith, <hi>I baptize with water, and he that comes after me baptizeth with the Holy Ghoſt, Mat.</hi> 3.11. And ſaith he, <hi>I baptize with water unto Repent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance,</hi>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:117808:9"/>that is, in order to Repentance, in the ſame Text: And all that were baptized with water, were not before baptized with the Holy Ghoſt, as <hi>Simon Magus, Demas,</hi> and others: This deſigne is but to exclude <hi>Infants,</hi> but <hi>I</hi> wave it.</p>
            <p>You come to my third Argument, for <hi>Sprinkling the baptized,</hi> becauſe that many were baptized in their Houſes, where Plung<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing could not be, as <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Cornelius,</hi> and others, <hi>Act.</hi> 9.17.18.10.22.27.48. To this you ſay, that <hi>I</hi> do ill to Father ſo many untruths in print upon the <hi>Scriptures;</hi> the <hi>Scriptures</hi> ſay not, that <hi>Paul</hi> was baptized in the houſe, but that <hi>Ananias</hi> entred in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the houſe, and putting his hands on Him, and immediately he aroſe and was baptized; But are you a Teacher in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and know not this? Can you teach others, and not teach your ſelfe? Did <hi>Ananias</hi> enter into the houſe where <hi>Paul</hi> was, and lay His Hand upon him, and immediately he was baptized? What ſay you to this word, Mr Doctor, <hi>immediately?</hi> or at the twinkling of an eye, or at the very ſame inſtant of time, he was baptized? <hi>I</hi> think the ſubtilleſt Plunger amongſt you cannot finde time, out of that word <hi>immediately,</hi> for <hi>Paul</hi> to goe out to bee plunged in ſome Pond or River: and beſides, <hi>Paul</hi> was faln upon the earth, and was three days without ſight, and did neither eat nor drink, <hi>Act.</hi> 9.4, 9. Now Mr Doctor, what do you think of this man? was he able to goe out? You ſhewe your ſelfe a very unskilfull Doctor, if you ſay, <hi>Yea;</hi> deſerving to be caſt out of the Colledg for a Novice: What, neither eat nor drink for three dayes toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther? and in this condition you would have him plunged into a river. Well, it is a mercy that wee have other Doctors of better Judgement, that wee may not depend upon ſuch Novices. But you ſay, <hi>Paul was not to ſit ſtill to be ſprinkled, but,</hi> ſaith the Text, <hi>riſe up, why tarryeſt thou? ariſe, and be baptized, Act.</hi> 22.16. But where is your Syllogiſm Mr Doctor? becauſe hee being faln on the earth, and <hi>Ananias</hi> haſtens him to ariſe and bee baptized, therefore hee went out to ſome River with his Hands upon him? and all this in the twinkling of an eye. Well Sir, conſider, and lay to heart, who it is that fathers <hi>untruths upon the Scriptures.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And for <hi>Cornelius</hi> and others, the Text miſquoted, which ſhould be, <hi>Act.</hi> 10.22, 23, 27, 48. where it is ſaid, <hi>That Corne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:117808:9"/>being warned of God by an Angel, to ſend for thee,</hi> meaning <hi>Peter, to come into his houſe, and to heare words of thee: Then called he them in, and he went in and found many that were come together, and he commanded them to be baptized.</hi> Now Mr Doctor what will you do to evade this truth? I have proved, that they came into the houſe of <hi>Cornelius:</hi> but a Conclave of plunging Doctors cannot ſhew me that they went out to be plunged: but you ſay <hi>Peter</hi> reaſoned the buſineſs, and then ſaid, <hi>Who can forbid water?</hi> he commanded them to be baptized: but it is not ſaid, where, or when: ſo then you grant that here is a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand to baptize, being in the houſe, and no Command to go out: then which is the way to fulfil the Command, but to baptize them where they were? and that is in the houſe of <hi>Cornelius:</hi> but then you ſay, If this was done with water, as is expreſſed, the Apoſtles muſt carry it with them in Aquavitae bottles, or Roſe-water-bottles, to daſh them in the face as ſoon as they had been taken confeſſing of Chriſt: But Sir, how will you make it out, that <hi>Cornelius</hi> had no veſſels in his houſe for water till <hi>Peter</hi> came with his Aquavitae bottle, or Strong-water-bottle? we look for proof, Mr Doctor, elſe you had as good ſay nothing: But all your hopes is of the Jaylor, whom you ſuppoſe is the moſt likely to be plunged; for you ſuppoſe that I have not read the 30 verſe of the 16 Chapter of the <hi>Acts,</hi> for there it is ſaid, <hi>And brought them out;</hi> but I demand to know out of what, for it is ſaid, verſ. 32. <hi>They ſpake unto him the Word of the Lord: And in the ſame hour of the night he took them, and waſhed their ſtripes, and was baptized he and all his, ſtraightway,</hi> verſ. 33. <hi>And when he had brought them into his Houſe, he ſet meat before them,</hi> verſ, 34. And the Magiſtrates ſent to the keeper of the priſon to let them go, and they refuſed: Therefore that firſt <hi>out</hi> of ver. 30. was but out of one room into another, and the keepers houſe was in the priſon; ſo that from firſt to laſt the Apoſtles were not out of the priſon, till the laſt verſe, then indeed <hi>they went out of the priſon, and entered into the houſe of Lydia.</hi> Now, Mr Doctor, who ſpeaks contrary to the Text? then you ſay, the blood of <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Silas:</hi> Abſurdities muſt not be put upon the Scriptures: Here you would ſay ſomething, although you ſee an error in the printing, naming the 48 verſe, when as there is
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:117808:10"/>but 40 in the Chapter, yet from this you ſay, that my partiallity appears in not asking the ſame queſtions about waſhing <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Silas,</hi> as about the Baptiſm of the Jaylor and his houſhold, as what veſſel had they? and who fetched the water? and how often emptied? Did <hi>Paul</hi> ſtand in the veſſel? How many times went he in? or was he in at all? But here I ſee that you may miſtake, or the Printer, for you mentioning <hi>Paul,</hi> when I ſpeak of <hi>Peter:</hi> only this I ſay, Who fetched all that water the ſame hour of the nigh for the Jaylor and his houſhold, they being ſtill in priſon, and at midnight, and all that ſpeaking the Word of the Lord, and waſhing their ſtripes, was done the ſame hour, being unpoſſible, if they had gone out to be plunged with Lanthorns and Torches, and all little enough to eſcape drownding: but I ſay, all the reſt is ſpoken of <hi>Peter</hi> baptizing 3000 perſons toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther after his Sermon, <hi>Acts</hi> 2.41. Now you do wiſely to wave this Text, being no ways able to evade it: in your next, I pray you, ſpeak your mind on that Text, and you ſhall hear further from me; alſo you ſhould have made Anſwers to thoſe Queries, but it ſeems you could not.</p>
            <p>Then you come to my fourth Argument, which is this, The Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments muſt be adminiſtred where the Word is preached, becauſe <hi>preach and baptize</hi> are put together, <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.19. And many were baptized in their houſes immediately after Jeſus Chriſt was preached unto them, as <hi>Cornelius,</hi> and others, <hi>Acts</hi> 10. and 2.41. To this you ſay, the Word is Diſcipline, or make Diſciples bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizing them: But I ſay, the ſame Commiſſion by <hi>Mark</hi> is, <hi>Go ye <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> to all the world, and preach the Goſpel, Mark</hi> 16.15. He or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dain'd twelve, that they ſhould be with him, and that he might fend them forth to preach, <hi>Mark</hi> 3.14. Now ſet theſe Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures together, and the reſult will be, to make Diſciples, by preaching; this one truth, if well obſerved, would confound all the Sectaries Convincticles, who admit members on other terms then by preaching the Goſpel, by a private Confederacy among themſelves, to admit the rich on eaſie terms, and hold the poor to hard terms, yea to admit for great ſums of money, ſo did not the Apoſtles: But you go on, denying my Argument, ſaying, Both <hi>Iohn</hi> the Baptiſt, and Chriſt, and his Diſciples, went up and down preaching in the Wilderneſs, and about <hi>Galilee,</hi> and in a
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:117808:10"/>Mountain, and in a Charriot, but they baptized in <hi>Jordan</hi> in <hi>Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non,</hi> &amp;c. To this I anſwer, All thoſe were travelling, as you ſay; now their caſe and ours is not the ſame: as for example, the Lord ſaith, <hi>He that is eight days old let him be circumciſed, Gen.</hi> 17.12. But the caſe was not ſo when they were travelling in the Wilderneſs, yea it was laid aſide all that time, <hi>Ioſh.</hi> 5.7. but they muſt not do ſo in <hi>Canaan:</hi> Now I am ſpeaking of <hi>Canaan,</hi> and not of the Wilderneſs, and alſo of thoſe Miniſters who are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fin'd to a place, and charged with one Flock; and if you can ſhew me that ſuch do preach in one place, and baptize in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, you ſay ſomething, if not, you muſt not imitate our fixed Miniſters for a ſubſiſtance only, when your judgment is for thoſe univerſal Miniſters; but rather a way to other parts, having but one coat, no chrip, nor money in your purſe, and eat what is ſet before you, and in this condition carry no Aquavitae bottles, nor Roſe-water-bottles with you. <hi>Hapy is he that condemneth not himſelf in the thing that he alloweth: He that doubteth, is damned if he eat, becauſe he eateth not of faith; for whatſoever is not of faith is ſin, Rom.</hi> 14.22, 23. Do not trouble the fixed Churches of <hi>Canaan</hi> to bring them back again into the Wilderneſs, ſuch Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters are not for the welfare of <hi>Sion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I come to my fifth Argument, ſhewing the inconveniences of Plunging: If a man ſtand on the bank to plunge the baptized under water, in ſo doing he may break his neck, if the water be ſhallow, and drownd him if it be deep; and if one ſtand in the water to ſave him, there muſt be two to baptize one man, flat againſt all examples in the Scriptures. To all this you ſay, that I ſprinkle my ſelf with holy water, and reſt in a contented igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance: Now for your cenſure I way it not, it is but one Doctors opinion; but yet I will ſhew you my ground for this Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: You will grant, that the Miniſters of the Goſpel have on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a right to adminiſter the Sacrament of Baptiſm, which you will confine to plunging, and not ſprinkling, therefore you ſay, they muſt plunge them into the water, they may not go into the water themſelves, but the Miniſter muſt plunge them in, or elſe he doth but half his duty and God will not accept any work that is done by partiallity, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.21. God will make thoſe Prieſts contemptible which are partial in his Law, <hi>Mal.</hi> 2.9. <hi>Are you
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:117808:11"/>not partial in your ſelves, and are become Judges of evil thoughts, Iam.</hi> 2.4. Therefore either leave pleading for plunging, or elſe do as you plead for ſhame, and ſtand on the bank and plunge them in, as they fling a dog into a ducking Pond, he muſt not wade in, the Miniſter muſt plunge him in.</p>
            <p>But I follow you to the ſixth Argument, againſt plunging the baptized, if naked, it is againſt modeſty, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.4. The Spouſe of Chriſt muſt be comely as <hi>Ieruſalem, Cant.</hi> 1.5. And it is a temptation; <hi>David</hi> was tempted by ſeeing a naked woman waſhing her ſelf, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 1.2, 4. And Chriſt hath taught us to ſay, <hi>Lead us not into temptation, Mat.</hi> 6. Neither may they have gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments for that uſe conſecrated as <hi>Aarons</hi> breeches, <hi>Exod.</hi> 28.42, 43. This would be as bad as the Prelates Surpleſs, and for wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men to wear them, being mans apparel, it were an abomination to the Lord, <hi>Deut.</hi> 22.5. Nor in their wearing clothes: The Jaylor feaſted the Apoſtles ſtraightway, <hi>Act.</hi> 16.34. Neither do we read, that they ſhifted themſelves before, nor after, nor that they ſate dung wet at meat with them: therefore to avoyd all theſe Abſurdities it muſt be granted, that they in Scripture were all ſprinkled with water, and not plunged under water. To this you ſay, What will I think of Circumciſion? but what you mean by it I know not, unleſs you mean that they were circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed naked; if this be your meaning, where is your proof? All is not gold that gliſters with him that hath his touch ſtone al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways by him: but ſuppoſe you think that they circumciſed them naked, yet the caſe is far different between the Jews and Chriſtians. Firſt, They circumciſed only males, but females are alſo baptized, <hi>Acts</hi> 8.12. Secondly, They circumciſed privately, but we baptize publickly. Thirdly, The father of the child did circumciſe, but the Miniſter muſt baptize; ſo that you ſee this will not help you at all: And it ſeems you are ſenſible of it, and therefore you fall to your prayer for me, but your prayer is to pervert me, and my prayer ſhall be, That God would be pleaſed to convince you of your error.</p>
            <p>I come to the ſeventh Argument, wherein I have ſhewed you the miſtake of the word <hi>baptize with water,</hi> not <hi>in water, Mat.</hi> 3.11. <hi>Joh.</hi> 1.33. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 5.26. <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.22. yea, to read <hi>in water,</hi> when it is ſaid <hi>with water,</hi> is as great an error, as to bow <hi>at the
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:117808:11"/>Name of Jeſus,</hi> in ſtead of <hi>in the Name of Jeſus:</hi> for mark the <hi>Scriptures</hi> wel; <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>When thou commeſt, bring my cloke with thee,</hi> not <hi>in thee,</hi> 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.16. <hi>Abraham</hi> ſaid to the young men, <hi>Abide here with the Aſſe, Gen.</hi> 22.5. not <hi>in the Aſſe;</hi> ſo baptize with water, not in the water: So on the other ſide, <hi>Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vi payd tythes in Abraham,</hi> not with <hi>Abraham; He was in the loynes of his father, when Melchizedec met him, Heb</hi> 7.9, 10. not with his loynes, when <hi>Melchizedec</hi> met him, and Chriſt ſaith, <hi>You beleeve in God, beleeve alſo in me, Joh.</hi> 14.1. not beleeve with God, and beleeve with mee: and ſo to baptize in the Name of Father, Son and Holy Ghoſt, not baptize with the Father, Son, and Holy Ghoſt; Chriſt never gave ſuch power to men: <hi>John</hi> ſaith, <hi>Hee, that is, Chriſt, baptizeth with the Holy Ghoſt:</hi> So where it is ſaid, <hi>Sprinkle the door poſts with the blood,</hi> not take the door poſts and plunge them in blood.</p>
            <p>To this you ſay that I affirme another untruth, for want of the knowledg of the Tongues, owning the errour of the Tranſlator, where <hi>John</hi> is made to ſay, <hi>I baptize with water;</hi> and you bid mee aske my Teachers, who know the Tongues, and they will tell me, that the Greek word ſignifieth in water, and not with water, yea, you will ſhew me two Texts for it, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 5.26. and <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.22. <hi>with the waſhing of water in the Word;</hi> but this is counterfeit coyn by my touchſtone: I muſt ſearch the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and ſee whether theſe things be ſo, as the noble <hi>Bereans</hi> did, <hi>Act.</hi> 17.11. I muſt take nothing upon truſt without tryal, and by my tryal I finde it thus, <hi>that he might ſanctifie and cleanſe it with the waſhing of water by the Word, Eph.</hi> 5.26. not in the Word: And the other Text is, <hi>with pure water, Heb.</hi> 10.22. not in pure water. Then you ſay, it were well if thoſe errors which are cauſed, for want of more exact Tranſlation, were taken away by a new Tranſlation; and till you are able to bee an Interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, it is good to be ſober in making your own concluſion upon matters of Interpretation, but yeeld to thoſe that are better able: To this I ſhall ſubmit, but I doubt you will not do ſo your ſelf; if you did, you would never turne preacher, nor gather a Church out of a Church, like ſheepſtealers, to make up your own flock, and think your ſelfe worthy of a better Calling then God hath appointed for you; certainly the end of ſuch will be miſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able.</p>
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:117808:12"/>
            <p>I come to the eighth Argument, <hi>Anabaptists who plead for plunging, condemne themſelves by their own practice, while they ſuffer the baptized to wade in half way, or to the middle, without their Teachers help, and then they plunge in the other half: Now either they muſt acknowledge, that the party doth and may baptize half himſelf, or elſe grant that the lower half was not at all baptizd, for their Miniſter did not put that under water; but our Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, holding the water over the baptized, doth put the baptized under water.</hi> To this you are moſt troubled at the word <hi>Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptist,</hi> and would have me to underſtand better what that word meanes, before I undertake to condemne any under that notion.</p>
            <p>And you ſay, when I underſtand the true ſignification of Baptiſme, then I will not exact brick, and allow no ſtraw, nor bid a man cut meat without a knife, nor expect that men ſhould be baptized, and not ſuffer them to come into the water. Sir, if I keep ſentinel, ſhew me your warrant from Jeſus Chriſt for your going into the water, or you paſſe not here; for wee have many now adayes that runne from their Rulers upon deſignes of their own, and it may be you are one of them, I may not let you paſſe into the water, neither is it meat that I keep from you, but poyſon; neither doe I exact any more from you then I allow you power and meanes to doe; uſe thoſe fewe drops according to the cuſtom of all Chriſtian Churches, and it is ſufficient; and he that ſhall adviſe you further, tell him we have no ſuch cuſtom, nor any of the Churches of God, although ſome will be contentious, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.16. Then you compare ſprinkling with <hi>Hocus Pocus,</hi> and call it ridiculous, but without proof, and that our Miniſters would not plead that as an Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, when as you ſee your reverend friend Mr <hi>Downame</hi> to own it; therefore I paſſe by theſe alſo as counterfeit coyn.</p>
            <p>And ſo I come to the laſt Argument, ſhewing, <hi>That ſprink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling one part is ſufficient, becauſe one drop is as truly water, as the whole Ocean Sea, and that no meaſure is preſcribed, onely it muſt be water, and the baptized may be under one drop, as well as under a tun; yet not as if there were any neceſſity to be under it, onely it muſt be applyed to the body, that our Faith may act upon the thing ſignified by it:</hi> But here you demand, <hi>For what is one drop ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient to feed Whales, to bear great ſhips, or to water the earth?
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:117808:12"/>Anſ.</hi> One drop is ſufficient to ſhew unto us that it is water; yea, that Element which Chriſt did appoint for the outward Form of Baptiſm, when ſet apart and conſecrated for that uſe by prayer: and it is our worke to obſerve the properties of water, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare them with the thing ſignified, thus, As water cooleth the heate, quencheth thirſt, cleanſeth away filth, maketh the Earth fruitful by watering of it; ſo the Spirit of Chriſt cooleth, ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfieth, cleanſeth, ſofteneth, maketh us fruitful in good workes. But Sir, if you will have that water into which you will bee planged, to doe all this, it were good you would plunge your Diſciples in the Ocean Sea; for it cannot bee that a River or Pond, which ſome plunge in, ſhould water the Earth, &amp;c. But you think to carry all away with Sophiſtry, thus; As one drop of water is water, therefore one part of the body is the body, and a hand is a foot: I am aſhamed of your Logique; yea, you deſerve to be caſt out of the Colledg for a Novice.</p>
            <p>But you go on; <hi>If one drop be ſufficient to ſhew that it is water, as well it is ſufficient to make dowe:</hi> But are theſe your rare gifts, which ſhould have beene publiſhed in <hi>Blacke-fryers</hi> Church? Surely you would have been hiſſed out with ſhame enough; and you are much bound to them that prevented it. But you ſay, <hi>John was in Aenon baptizing, becauſe there was much water there:</hi> Hence it ſeemes you would infer, that he plunged them into that water: But where is your Syllogiſme Mr Doctor? Will it fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, becauſe that <hi>John</hi> was baptizing in that Country where was much water, that therefore they were plunged into the water he was baptizing in <hi>Aenon,</hi> not in the water that was there.</p>
            <p>But you ſay, <hi>That I to little purpoſe ſay, the baptized may be under a drop, as well as under a tun:</hi> But I ſay the thing is a truth; yet, as I ſaid before, there is no neceſſity to bee under the water, onely it muſt be applyed to the body, for faith to be acted on the thing ſignified. But you ſay, <hi>If the dead were covered but with one graine of earth, each moſtrial would ſoone complaine there were not ſufficient:</hi> It is true, if you ſpeak of that Baptiſme, but I hope you will not bury folks alive, if you do, you are no Doctor for me, nor any friend of mine.</p>
            <p>I come to the Conference Chriſt had with <hi>Peter,</hi> about waſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of his feet, <hi>Joh.</hi> 23. <hi>Peter</hi> ſaith, <hi>Thou ſhalt never my feet,</hi>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:117808:13"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:117808:13"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:117808:14"/>Verſ. 8. <hi>But,</hi> ſaith <hi>Chriſt, if I waſh thee not, thou haſt no part with me:</hi> which ſhewes that this waſhing was Sacramental: then he would be plunged all over, Verſ. 9. But, ſaith <hi>Chriſt, that needeth not, becauſe he is clean every whit,</hi> Verſ. 10. Hence I ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that to neglect the duty is abominable, and to plunge all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver is more then ſufficient: Here you finde a word miſtaken by the Printer, ſaying, <hi>Thou haſt no part in me,</hi> which ſhould be <hi>with me;</hi> which could bee no deſigne of mine in it: but for this you ſay, almoſt all the <hi>Scriptures</hi> that I quote, I miſtake ſomething, which ſhewes the rankor of your ſpirit, but I paſſe it not. But then becauſe I ſay, that waſhing was Sacramental, you ſay, <hi>Why then doe not your Miniſters waſh the feete of Infants, rather then ſprinkle the face, which Chriſt never did? Anſ.</hi> Although it was <hi>Sacramental,</hi> to ſhew the ſignification of <hi>Baptiſme,</hi> yet to waſh the feet was not given in charge as a Rule for the Church, but on what part the <hi>Church</hi> ſhould ſee moſt convenient. Now the face is moſt convenient to be ſprinkled; Firſt, becauſe it is always bate, there needs no ſtripping, nor ſhifting for it. Secondly, It is the moſt honorable part, therefore the fitter for ſo honorable a ſervice. Thirdly, The face doth as it were repreſent all the man. Fourthly, On the face, to ſhew that we are not aſhamed of the <hi>covenant,</hi> bearing as it were the ſeal upon <hi>our face</hi> as an ornament or as frontlets between <hi>our eyes,</hi> as <hi>Job</hi> ſpeaketh. And beſides, this Sacrament was onely for the preſent occaſion, as the red ſea, the Cloud and the Rock was to <hi>Iſrael,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.2, 3.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> Now whereas <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> will ſay, <hi>when Ieſus was baptized, it is ſaid, he went out of the water, and Phillip and the Eunuch went both into the water, therefore they were plunged un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der water:</hi> My Anſwer was, that every pit or River in thoſe hot Countries was not always full to the brim, but ſometimes a man might goe downe into the pit or River to the water: But ſuppoſe they did wade into the water, yet that is not plunging under the water: and to wade in till they came where it was clear, and then to ſprinkle them in the Name of the <hi>Father, Sonne, and Holy Ghoſt,</hi> may very well ſtand with the Text.</p>
            <p>Then you fall to your prayer, to be delivered from the pit where no water is, namely, <hi>Ieremiahs</hi> pit, although not rightly quoted, which is, <hi>Ier.</hi> 38.6. as well you might have added <hi>Ioſephs</hi>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:117808:14"/>pit without water, <hi>Gen.</hi> 37.24. for theſe priſoners of hope, with the reſt of Gods People in <hi>Aegypt</hi> and <hi>Babylon,</hi> were brought forth, and double rendred unto them, <hi>Zach.</hi> 9.11, 12. for they as priſoners are gathered in the pit, and ſhut up in the priſon, yet after many days they were viſited, <hi>Iſai.</hi> 24.22. Thus God afflicts for our profit, to make us partakers of his holineſs, and to ſhew that he loves us, and that we are his children: Then why pray you ſo earneſtly to be kept from the pit of affliction, I doubt you had rather have the baſtards portion; ſee <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.6. to 11. I fear you have choſen iniquity, rather then affliction, <hi>Iob</hi> 36.21. But if you cauſe the righteous to go aſtray in an evil way, you ſhall fall into your own pit, <hi>Prov.</hi> 28.10. And I doubt it is the ſame with that of <hi>Oates,</hi> in <hi>Eſſex,</hi> out of which there was no deliverance, but preſent death, by drowning, for which at <hi>Chelmsford</hi> Sizes he had been hanged, if he had not made the better friends; therefore the pit of affliction is rather to be choſen, then the Anabaptiſts plunging pits, from which we ſhall ever pray, The Lord deliver us.</p>
            <p n="2">2. But they will ſay, That <hi>many came and were baptized of Iohn in Iordan, Mat.</hi> 3.6. and the Greek word ſhews that was by plunging.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> As before they might wade in, and yet be ſprinkled, and the Greek word as well ſignifies to ſprinkle as to plunge; but in regard plunging is accompanied with ſo many abſurdities, ſprinkling is rather to be choſen then plunging.</p>
            <p>To this you ſay, That all the Schollers in <hi>Europe</hi> cannot find it ſo in any Greek Author, nor others: Here is a bold challenge, ſuch another as you made to Doctor <hi>Gouge,</hi> when you dar'd him and all the Synod, to anſwer you: Now it were ſomething a hard task to ſeek for the judgment of all the Schollers in <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rope,</hi> yet I have one at hand, Mr <hi>Perkins</hi> in his Comentary on <hi>Galat.</hi> ſaith, <hi>That baptizing ſignifies not only waſhing the body by diving, but alſo by ſprinkling,</hi> pag. 214.26, 27. and I hold his judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment not inferior to Dr <hi>Chamberlains:</hi> But you ſay, If it were granted, hear would follow abſurdities, ſuch as theſe, <hi>In thoſe days came Iohn the Sprinkler, and ſprinkled in Iordan, and Iohn was ſprinkling in Aenon, and as many as have been plunged into Chriſt have put on Chriſt:</hi> But Sir, I hope you would be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:117808:15"/>if your Bible were thus tranſlated, <hi>Iohn the Plunger came preaching, and they were plunged of him in Iordan, and Iohn was plunging in Aenon, and as many at have been plunged into Chriſt, have put on Chriſt.</hi> This is your new Light that ſhould have been publiſhed in Black-Fryars Church.</p>
            <p>Then you ſay that I am not contented with theſe Abſurdities about plunging in water, but that I could add more, thus: Ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther this Ordinance muſt be laid aſide all the Winter, when as Chriſt never ſaid, Baptize in Summer and ceaſe in Winter, which would be a great prejudice to the Church; or elſe if obſerved, it would endanger the lines of thoſe that ſhould be ſo plunged. But you betake your ſelf to your old refuge, the Common-prayer book, and there you find a preſent Remedy for thoſe dangers, which is to baptize at <hi>Easter</hi> and <hi>Whitſuntide:</hi> But I ſay, then you would have many to be plunged together, and it may be ſome of them may have iſſues, or running ſores, or other loath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſom diſeaſes, frequent with Anabaptiſts, who hold all things common, and it may be ſome of them are not very cleanly, and ſo not fit to plunge the faces of ſome where the talls of others were newly waſhed in; this is not decently, nor in order, Mr Doctor.</p>
            <p n="3">3. But we are ſaid to be buried with Chriſt by Baptiſm, <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.4. therefore the baptized is to be plunged under water.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> In this Text is no mention made of baptizing with water, which is the outward form of Baptiſm, only we are ſaid to be baptized into the death of Chriſt, and after death buried with him by Baptiſm: Now Jeſus Chriſt a long time after he was baptized of <hi>Iohn</hi> in <hi>Iordan,</hi> ſaith, <hi>I have a Baptiſm to be bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized with, Luk.</hi> 12.50. which was his death and burial; and he ſaith to the ſons of <hi>Zebedee, Ye ſhall drink of my Cup, and be bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized with my Baptiſm, Mat.</hi> 20.23. that is, they ſhall dye, and be buried, and riſe again at the laſt day; and alſo in this life they ſhall receive the things ſignified, that is, the body of ſin ſhall dye by the death of Chriſt, and their ſinne ſhall be buried or covered by the burial of Chriſt, and they ſhall riſe to newneſs of life by the Reſurrection of Chriſt; and theſe are all expreſſed in that text, <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.2, 4. This is <hi>the doctrine of Baptiſms,</hi> ſpoken <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.2. but I ſay here is no mention of the Form of Baptiſm, therefore
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:117808:15"/>no warrant from this Text to plunge the baptized under water. Now if we ſhould bring all thoſe Texts that ſpeake of Baptiſm, to prove the outward Forme, wee ſhould runne into ſuch a laby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinth, that wee ſhould not bee able to get out: as for example, <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeakes of baptizing the dead, ſaying, <hi>If the dead riſe not at all, why are they then baptized for the dead,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.25. Now although here be more in this Text to prove the Forme of Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme, then in that <hi>Rom.</hi> 6. yet wee may not at all ground any Forme of Baptiſme from it: firſt, becauſe the party is dead, and ſo unfit to make a member of the Church by that ſolemne admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance. Secondly, Any woman may waſh the body when it is dead, but none may baptize any Chriſtian with that Form of Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm given to the Church, but the Miniſters of the Goſpel, which are ſent to preach and baptize, <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.19. Thirdly, This waſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the dead carcaſſe was done without any words of inſtitution, therefore not the Form of Baptiſm given to the Church: There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore from ſuch Texts as theſe we have no warrant to plunge the <hi>baptized</hi> in or under the water.</p>
            <p>To all this you ſay, <hi>when I bid my man waſh a cup or glaſſe, doth it ſignifie nothing, unleſſe I bid him doe it with water? Let him that is diligent ſo reade and ſatisfie himſelfe with the Texts, Rom.</hi> 6.4. <hi>Col.</hi> 2.12. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.6. <hi>Anſw. Baptiſme</hi> doth not always ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie waſhing, but <hi>Death</hi> and <hi>Burial,</hi> and ſometimes <hi>Doctrines, Act.</hi> 18.25. neither doth <hi>waſhing</hi> always ſignifie <hi>baptizing,</hi> for then if you ſhould ſay to your man, <hi>waſh my cup,</hi> it were all one as to ſay, <hi>baptize my cup:</hi> and ſo your wife might ſay to her maid, <hi>baptize my diſhes, when they are foul.</hi> But theſe New-Lights are nothing but palpable darkneſſe from the Prince of Dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</p>
            <p>Then you tell me, <hi>that you will not be at the charges of printing a Satisfaction to every one that ſcribles, having ſpent and loſt ſo much for the Publique, and repayd with ſo much Injuſtice and Ingratitude; nor will you meddle at preſent with the law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe or unlawfulneſſe of your Miniſtry,</hi> not His it ſeemes: Now if your loſſes be ſo great, why did you print at all? and who doe you blame for your loſſes, and that requitall of <hi>Injuſtice and Ingratitude?</hi> And then you begge a praiſe
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:117808:16"/>of your patience, and excuſe your pride, and pray to winne mee to the Trueths of God in Chriſt: To this Prayer I ſhall joyne with you in that word <hi>Amen,</hi> and then I am ſure, if the Lord heare and grant it, I ſhall never turne <hi>Anabaptist.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>
                     <hi>May</hi> 2. 1650.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <p>
               <hi>Imprimatur,</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>I. D.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
